Guide to the Potter Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Potter family papers
1823-1888
MS 16
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
1.5
(5 boxes)
Account books (1846-1868) relating to surveying and highway repair in Hamden, Conn.; ledgers, daybooks, and pay books concerning the breeding of cattle, sale of hides and wood, and quarrying of stone; accounts (1825-1882) of the firm Rowe and Tuttle of Fair Haven, Conn., covering the sale of general merchandise; and deeds for land acquired by the Potter family in North Branford, New Haven, North Haven, Fair Haven, and Hamden, Conn.Represented in the collection are Jabez Turner Potter (1796-1871), Evelyn Blakeslee, Philemon Blakeslee, Lemuel Potter, Timothy Potter (b.1769), Martha (Turner) Potter, Sherman Benjamin Potter (1806-1860), Timothy Potter (1792-1853), Merritt Luzerne Potter (b.1831), George Washington Potter (1802-1879), and Timothy Zalmon Potter (b.1832).
Potter family
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
I. Legal Records. II. Correspondence. III. Financial Records.
Scope and Contents
The Potter Family Papers, 1795-1887, are mainly the financial records and deeds of Jabez Turner Potter, 1796-1871. A surveyer of Hamden, Connecticut, his ledgers record payments to laborers, accounts as collector of highway taxes, sales of farm produce, oysters, hides and wood, and contracting work such as road repair, quarrying and carting stone, and masonry on houses and stores. Most of the papers and records date from the 1840's through the 1860's. There are also six volumes of accounts, 1825-1882, apparently all kept in the same hand, of a general store in the vicinity of Fair Haven, North Haven, or Hamden, Conn. The proprietors may have been Rowe & Tuttle, since large sums of money were regularly drawn from the business through the Rowe & Tuttle account. The store of John Rowe and Smith Tuttle was the principal store in Fair Haven, now a section of New Haven. However, the connection between Rowe & Tuttle and the Potter Family is uncertain. It is known that Smith Tuttle's sister, Mercy, married in 1810 Isaac Blakeslee, whose twin sons, Lucius Merrick Blakeslee and Julius Merritt Blakeslee, were clerks for, or in business with their uncle, Smith Tuttle. In 1885, Jabez Turner Potter's daughter, Eliza Ann (1826-) married another Isaac Blakeslee, probably a relative of the elder Blakeslee (see Potter Genealogy, Part V, p. 2 and Tuttle Genealogy, p. 284). The parents of the donor of these papers, Georgina Johnson, were George A. and Mary (Blakeslee) Johnson. The day books and ledger record the sale of groceries and general merchandise and goods received.
Box 1 of the papers contains 13 folders of deeds, 1795-1870, for land in New Haven, North Haven, Fair Haven, Hamden, East Haven, and North Branford. Most of the deeds are those of Jabez Potter. Other Potter relatives and prominent area citizens cited in the deeds are: Elmon, Evelyn, and Philemon Blakeslee; Frederick Croswell; Caleb Mix; Hervey and Eliza Treat; Jared Foot; and Lemuel, Timothy (b.1796?), Timothy (1792-1853), Martha (Turner), and Sherman Benjamin (1806-1860) Potter.
The Potter Family Papers include very little correspondence and are primarily a source of information on the economic and agricultural history of Hamden and surrounding towns.
Business; Families; Working class; Connecticut -- Commerce; Connecticut; Fair Haven (Conn.); Hamden (Conn.); New Haven (Conn.); North Haven (Conn.); Account books; Deeds; Businessmen; Labor movement; Labor; Blakeslee, Evelyn; Blakeslee, Philemon; Potter, George Washington, 1802-1879; Potter, Jabez Turner, 1796-1871; Potter, Lemuel; Potter, Martha Turner; Potter, Merritt Luzerne, 1831-; Potter, Sherman Benjamin, 1806-1860; Potter, Timothy Zalmon, 1832-; Potter, Timothy, 1769-; Potter, Timothy, 1792-1853; Tuttle, Smith, 1795-1865; Potter family; Rowe and Tuttle
- LEGAL RECORDS, 1795, 1802, 1814, 1818-1870; Series I; 0.25
  Scope and Contents
  Legal records contains deeds and miscellaneous materials. The deeds are arranged by families with the Potter deeds first followed by other families in alphabetical order.
  Miscellaneous includes a court decision concerning Jabez Turner Potter's military service, power of attorney, the Pierpont estate settlement, and agreements for construction work.
  - Deeds
    - Potter, Jabez Turner, 1818-1870 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Potter, Hannah, 1851 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Potter, Horace, 1824 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Potter, Lemuel, 1814 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Potter, Martha, 1795 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Potter, Timothy, b. 1796?, 1802 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Blakeslee, Elmon, 1823-1869 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Blakeslee, Evelyn, 1831, 1834 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Blakeslee, Philemon Jr., 1830 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Foot, Jared, 1828-1839 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Maynard, William, 1814 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Treat, Eliza, 1863 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Treat, Harvey, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Potter, Jabez Turner, court decision concerning his military service, 1828-1833 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Power of Attorney, 1836, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Pierpont estate settlement record, 1852, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Agreements of construction work, to be done, 1845, 1853 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1848-1849, 1852-1853, 1866, 1875; Series II; 0.25
  Correspondence contains material to Jabez Turner Potter from Abram Ehle, George W. Potter and Timothy Z. Potter arranged in chronological order for each individual.
  Fragments of correspondence are found at the end of the series.
  - Potter, Jabez Turner from Abram Ehle, 1846-1848 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Potter, Jabez Turner from George W. and Timothy Z. Potter, 1849, 1852-1853 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Fragments of correspondence, 1866, 1875 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- FINANCIAL RECORDS, 1825-1889; Series III; 1.5 linear feet (4 Boxes)
  This series is arranged according to type of record: ledger, daybooks, account books, bills and miscellaneous.
  Miscellaneous contains promissory notes, premium notes, receipts, an arithmetic books and a death certificate.
  Jabez Turner Potter's general bills are in chronological order at the beginning of the section with his specific bills chronologically arranged next. These are followed by Blakeslee bills and miscellaneous.
  - Ledger of a general store (possibly of Rowe & Tuttle), 1825-1834 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Daybooks
    - Of a general s[illegible]re (possibly of Rowe & Tuttle) in the vicinity of Fair Haven, North Haven, or Hamden, Conn., 1825-1830, 1834 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Same, 1830-1863, 1882 (Box 3, Folder 23-26)
  - Account Books
    - Miscellaneous accounts, 1859-1861 (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Accounts with laborers, 1847-1854, 1856, 1858, 1860 (Box 4, Folder 28-31)
    - Accounts with laborers, also for carrying stones; with some entries of family births and deaths, 1859-1862, 1868 (Box 4, Folder 32)
    - Accounts as collector of highway taxes and account of highway repair, 1859-1860 (Box 4, Folder 33)
    - Accounts as collector of highway taxes; also, few accounts with laborers, 1862-1866, 1868 (Box 4, Folder 34)
    - Accounts for household; also for work done, 1847, 1865-1866 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Accounts with real estate, 1867 (Box 4, Folder 36)
    - Accounts of oyster sales; also bull servicing, and some laborers, 1842,1846-1851 (Box 4, Folder 37)
    - Accounts with laborers, stone quarrying, materials; also some for Ellfskin s[illegible]es, and bulls (Potter and Atwater), 1847-1857,1859,1863,1870-1871 (Box 4, Folder 38)
    - Accounts for quarrying and carting stone; also a few extra entries (Bishop and Potter), 1851,1853,1858;1867 (Box 4, Folder 39)
    - Accounts for quarrying and carting stone, 1853 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Bills
    - Potter, Jabez Turner, 1835-1858 (Box 4, Folder 41-43)
    - Potter, Jabez Turner, 1859-1889, undated (Box 5, Folder 44)
    - Potter, Jabez Turner, concerning the Oyster Schooners and sloops, 1841-1848 (Box 5, Folder 45)
    - Potter, Jabez Turner, concerning early railroads, 1843-1865 (Box 5, Folder 46)
    - Potter, Jabez Turner, concerning the construction of a house for Mrs. Eliza Treat, 1870 (Box 5, Folder 47)
    - Bishop and Potter, 1853, undated (Box 5, Folder 48)
    - Potter, Merritt Luzerne (1831-), 1858-1880, undated (Box 5, Folder 49)
    - Blakeslee, Mrs. Eliza Ann (Potter)(1826-), 1851-1859 (Box 5, Folder 50)
    - Miscellaneous, unidentified bills and notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Promissory notes, 1834-1885 (Box 5, Folder 53)
    - Premium notes of insurance policies, 1851, 1854 (Box 5, Folder 54)
    - Potter, Merritt Luzerne, receipts for tuition paid to school district no, 9 at Hamden, Connecticut, 1857-1871 (Box 5, Folder 55)
    - Arithmetic book with problems, unidentified, 18th century (Box 5, Folder 56)
    - LeRowland, Janice, death certificate, 1874 (Box 5, Folder 57)